Preliminary Guide to the Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter Records, 1975-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter records 1975-2004 and undated
Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter
5.4 linear feet Extent: 2973 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00051
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Art Libraries Society of North America Southeast Chapter Papers, 1975-2001 and undated were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002.
Biographical Note
ARLIS/SE was founded in 1974 as a chapter within the Southern Region of the Art Libraries Society of North America (ARLIS/NA founded 1972, Chicago). Members primarily come from the states of North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, Georgia, Florida, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, Puerto Rico, and the American Virgin Islands. A Regional Representative is appointed by ARLIS/NA to the Southern Region / SE Chapter and serves a two-year term. This Representative serves as a liaison between the Chapter and the Executive Board.
The Chapter is involved in several activities. It issues a Newsletter, now called ARTifacts, hosts an online discussion list and web site, and holds a Conference annually somewhere within the Southeast region. In addition, its members participate in the ARLIS/NA Annual Conference, including hosting the Annual Conference in the Southeast in 1996 (Miami Beach). A major activity of the Chapter is its LoPresti Publicatoin Award Competition, established in 1985 to recognize and encourage excellence in art publications issued in the Southeastern United States. This annual award is named for Mary Ellen LoPresti (d. 1985), who was the Design Librarian at North Carolina State University.
Collection Overview
The collection (acc#2002-168) (2250 items, 4.2 lin. ft.; dated 1975-2001 and undated) includes chapter correspondence, bylaws, annual reports, membership lists, photographs, conference materials, LoPresti Awards (for excellence in art publication), and some financial records. Scattered throughout are materials and correspondence related to the national organization. There are 20 electronic files on one floppy disk that have been migrated to the electronic records server. In addition there are 20 black-and-white photos and two transparencies.
Addition (08-058) (700 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1984-2003) includes membership rosters, treasury materials, annual meeting minutes, and bylaws.
Subject Headings
Art Libraries Society of North America; Art Libraries Society of North America; Art Libraries Society of North America. Southeast Chapter; ARLIS/SE; ARLIS/NA; Black-and-white photographs; Machine-readable records; Transparencies; Art Libraries Society of North America; Art Libraries Society of North America
Contents of Collection
- Accession 2001-0168
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - LoPresti Awards
      - 1992-1999 (Box 1)
      - Guidelines, 1984; 1991; 1999 (Box 1)
      - Award and entry form graphics, 1992 and undated (Box 1)
      - Raffle Tickets, undated (Box 1)
    - Strategic Plan
      - Executive Board approval, 1991 July (Box 1)
      - 1996-1999 (Issued December 1996 Dec.) (Box 1)
    - Chapter Success Book, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Annual Conferences
      - Final Reports 15th Washington D.C., 1987 (Box 1)
      - Proceedings 24th Miami Beach, FL, 1996 (Box 1)
      - Preliminary Program San Antonio, TX, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Conference Planning Manual, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Membership brochures, 1994 Oct. and undated (Box 1)
    - Chapter Officers list, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Proposal for 1991 ARLIS/NA meeting in Charleston, SC, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
      - Letters to ARLIS/NA re: invitation to hold 1996 meeting in Miami Beach, 1992 (Box 2)
      - General, 1991-2000 (Box 2)
      - Letterhead and envelopes, blank, undated (Box 2)
    - Bylaws, 1991 Revision; 1999-2000 memos re: proposed changes (Box 2)
    - Membership
      - Lists, ca. 1990-1991 (Box 2)
      - Lists, 1997 (Box 2)
      - Lists, 1998 (Box 2)
      - Forms, 1999 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1996 and undated (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences
      - Sarasota, 1985
        - Graphics for t-shirt design (Box 2)
        - Photographs (Box 2)
      - Charlotte, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Tampa, 1991 (Box 2)
      - Durham, 1992 (Box 2)
      - Birmingham, 1994 (Box 2)
      - Clemson, 1995 (Box 2)
      - Augusta, 1996 (Box 2)
      - New Orleans, 1997 (Box 2)
      - Sarasota, 1998
        - Information (Box 2)
        - Photographs (Box 2)
      - Atlanta, 25th Anniversay, 1999
        - Pre-conference Survey (Box 2)
        - Brochure, including mock-up (Box 2)
        - Correspondence (Box 2)
        - Registration (Box 2)
        - Election (Box 2)
        - Speakers (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Raleigh-Durham, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1985, 1991 (Box 2)
      - Regional Representative's Report to Executive Board, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - ARLIS/SE Newsletter, 1989 Feb.-1997 Fall (Box 2)
      - ARTifacts 1998 Feb.-2001 June (Box 2)
    - LoPresti Awards, 1985-1990, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - National Conference
      - 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - National Conference Task Force, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - Secretary/Treasurer Duties, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Stationery Designs, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
    - Annual Reports and Newsletters, 1975-1993 (Box 3)
    - ARLIS/NA Mailings, 1977-1989 (Box 3)
    - Bylaws
      - 1976-1984 (Box 3)
      - 1988, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Membership Application Forms, 1980-1987 (Box 3)
    - ARLIS/NA Pre Conference Meeting, 1993 (Box 3)
    - ARLIS/NA Membership Directory Forms, 1992 (Box 3)
    - ARLIS/NA Flyers, undated (Box 3)
    - Membership Lists, 1977-1994 (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Elsie Straight, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Floyd Zula, 1989 (Box 4)
      - [Material from envelope] (Box 4)
      - Marica Duncan, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Maryellen LoPresti, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Ray Abell, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Formation, Leslie Friedman, 1975 (Box 4)
      - Darla Rushing, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Stephen Patrick, 1980 (Box 4)
      - ARLIS/NA, 1980-1981 and undated (Box 4)
      - ARLIS/SE, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Chapter Idea Exhange, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Other Chapter meeting announcements and newsletters, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - News of members phone calls, etc., 1981 (Box 4)
    - Publicity and Membership Lists, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Membershiop Forms, Bylaws, Annual Reports, Meeting notices and Chapter Mailings, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Banking and Finances
      - ARLIS/NA SE Finances, 1993 (Box 5)
      - ARLIS/NA SE Finances, 1994-1996, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Finances, March (Box 5)
      - Banking, 1978-1981 (Box 5)
      - Banking, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - ARLIS/SE Mailing Lists and Menu's, 1994 (Box 5)
    - ARLIS Dues and Registration, 1993 (Box 5)
    - ARLIS/NA New Members in Southeast (Box 5)
    - Treasurer's Reports (Box 5)
    - ARLIS/SE Name Changes, etc., 1993 (Box 5)
    - Idea Book, 1992 (Box 5)
    - ARLIS/NA Chapter Duties and Procedures (Box 5)
    - Art Publication Awards (Box 5)
    - ARLIS/NA Funded Projects, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Stationery (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Misc. (Box 6)
    - Correspondence
      - Philip Rees, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
      - Bill Clayton, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
      - Edward Teague, 1986-1989 (Box 6)
      - Yvonne Morse, 1985 (Box 6)
      - Leslie Abrams, 1984 (Box 6)
      - Jill Sloop, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Margaret Knoerr, 1982 (Box 6)
      - Ann Ross, 1991 (Box 6)
      - Sara Wolf, 1990 (Box 6)
    - ARLIS/SE Agenda Meeting, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Receipt Book, 1994 (Box 6)
- Accession (2008-0058) 1984-2003, (2 boxes)
  Addition (08-058) (700 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1984-2003) includes membership rosters, treasury materials, annual meeting minutes, and bylaws.
  - Conference and meeting minutes, 1984-1997 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE 27th Annual Conference, Nov. 2001 (Box 7)
  - Sun Trust Business Accounts, 2002-2003 (Box 7)
  - Conference information, 2003 (Box 7)
  - New Orleans conference, 2003 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE secretary and treasurer, 2003 (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE treasurer bank account, Nexity (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE treasurer checking account (Box 7)
  - Membership, 2003 [zip disk, removed and copied onto electronic records server] (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE by-laws, treasury documents, etc., 1998-2002 (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - ARLIS/SE treasury checking (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - ARLIS/SE membership, 2000-2003 (5 folders, 1 money receipt book) [3 floppy disks removed and copied onto electronic records server] (Box 8)